We are starting
on ל"ז עמוד א', Lamed Zayin Amud Aleph, today's דף daf is
ל"ז, Lamed Zayin, top of the דף, daf, the משנה. Mishnah. Let's
take a look.
So we are finally putting aside טהרות Taharos and זרעים Zroim and
etcetera and we are now talking, we are now getting on, or
whatever, it's always טהרות Taharos and now getting back to שחיטה. Shechitah.
So let's take a look. And this משנה Mishnah actually is a
great משנה Mishnah because as the גמרא Gemara analyzes it, gets into
fundamental conceptual distinctions, Halachic distinctions between טרפה, Treifah, נבלה, Neveilah, and an
animal that's about to die. So let's take a look. Okay, השוחט
המסוכנת, Hashocheit Hamisukenes, you שחט shacht an animal that is in danger,
that is about to drop dead from old age. Not a טרפה,
Treifah, but it is about to die. Right, not endangered species. So
what's the story? So רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר עד
שתפרכס ביד וברגל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer ad shetiparkes beyad uveragel,
after you שחט shacht it or sometime towards the end of שחיטה,
Shechitah, we'll see about that in tomorrow's דף, daf, you have to
see it have some type of a thrashing in its death, while
not death rattle, some type of a thrashing to indicate that there
was enough life left to it actually before you finished שחט shacting
it. The concern is since it was about to die, excuse me,
maybe it died a second too soon. You know, maybe it died
before you finished the שחיטה. Shechitah. So therefore, in order to show
that it did not die before you finished the שחיטה, Shechitah, you
have to see that there was some sign of still some life
force in it as the שחיטה Shechitah is terminated. Now when exactly
is that point? In the middle of the שחיטה, Shechitah, towards the
end of the שחיטה Shechitah and so on. But here, this is
specifically about an animal that was about to die. If it's a
normal animal, if it has no motion when you שחט shacht it,
doesn't matter, but this animal you have to see had some life
force in it at the moment of שחיטה. Shechitah.
A foreleg and a back leg?
Yes, exactly. Thank you. Okay, and what's the kind
of the status of whether the animal can be כשר kosher like
a טרפה? Treifah?
No, correct. The basic assumption is a מסוכנת misukenes is כשר kosher
and that's going to lead the גמרא Gemara into a discussion about
the difference between a טרפה, Treifah, a נבלה, Neveilah, and a מסוכנת.
misukenes. Okay, a טרפה Treifah is basically an animal that won't live
but because of an injury. This is just an animal that's dying
of old age or of cancer or something of that sort. Okay,
so the only concern is did it drop dead before you finished
שחט shacting it? So therefore it has to have some type of
a thrashing of the hand and of the foot in order to
show at the moment during at the end of, we'll see in
the גמרא, Gemara, שחיטה Shechitah to show that it still had life
in it even as the שחיטה Shechitah was terminated. רבי אליעזר אומר
דייה אם זינקה. Rebbi Eliezer omer dayah im zinkah. It is enough
if it, if it squirted blood. That shows enough life force in
it. ודייה אם זינקה, Ve'dayah im zinkah, did I say? No, אמר
רבי שמעון, Amar Rebbi Shimon, so רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon said, השוחט
בלילה, Hashocheit balaylah, you שחט shacht at night and you couldn't see
if it was doing any, this type of an animal, and you
couldn't see if it did any of these movements, ולמחר השכים ומצא
כותלים מלאים דם, Ule'machar hishkim umatza kosalim mele'im dam,
and in the morning you woke up and you found the walls
filled with blood, splattered with blood, כשרה, kisherah, you know it's כשר
kosher שזינקה shezinkah
because you know that it must have squirted blood. וכמידת רבי אליעזר,
Uchimidas Rebbi Eliezer, this is according to the position of רבי אליעזר
Rebbi Eliezer that squirting blood suffices. So even though you didn't see
it squirt blood, I mean how else did the walls get filled
with blood? Now as the גמרא Gemara is going to say, although
obviously it does sound like it's the walls of the house or
wherever you were שחט, shacting, the barn, the גמרא Gemara is going
to say that it really just means כותלי בית השחיטה, koslei beis
hashechitah, the walls of the place of שחיטה, shechitah, meaning that's a
phrase used which means basically the place of the cut. It's the
where the nut, where the neck has been cut, which is funny
because you would say, I mean obviously some blood is going to
come out. So but the גמרא Gemara is going to interpret this
in a very as a very sort of low threshold, low criteria,
that even if just the walls of the neck of the, you
know, of the cut are filled with blood, you can assume this
squirting occurred. Okay, I you know it's questionable whether that's פשט pshat
in the משנה. Mishnah. Okay, but that's anyway, that's רבי אליעזר Rebbi
Eliezer working off, רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon working off of רבי אליעזר.
Rebbi Eliezer. מלאים דם, Mele'im dam, you know?
Right, right, filled with blood, good point.
Does the blood have to trap into something?
Not, no, in theory
it could, I mean you could try to do it hygienically but
Halachically it doesn't have to, there's no דין din of כסוי הדם
kisui hadam by a בהמה. beheimah.
But if the animal is sick and dying, what do you want
to שחט? shacht?
If the animal is what? No, that's exactly why you want to
שחט, shacht, because if you don't שחט, shacht, all that meat is
going to go to waste. So here you have a two-thousand-pound animal
that's about to drop dead on you, you let it drop dead,
you have to whatever sell it as dog meat or you know
you can't sell it to Jews, you can't sell it as כשר
kosher meat. If you שחט shacht it, you can salvage the meat.
But you can only sell it for dog meat.
If it died, if you didn't שחט shacht it, but if you
שחט shacht it you can sell it as כשר. kosher.
I am just saying
if the animal is sick.
Yeah, well, if it's sick you're right, it probably would not be
wise health decision, unless it's not sick, let's say it's just dying
of old age.
Oh, old age is different, okay, but
you're right, I also gave an example of cancer, that's true.
Okay, but still saying if it's sick you can still eat it.
Technically, I mean it's not smart as Joe is saying, but that's
true. Okay, let's keep on going. וחכמים אומרים, Vechachamim omrim, and the
Rabbis say, עד שתפרכס או ביד או ברגל. ad shetiparkes o beyad
o beragel. No. How you don't need both the hind and back
leg, either of the front leg or the back leg, it shows
some thrashing. Oh, until it... because the first one said you needed
both.
No, no, I'm saying, why is this different?
They disagree. It's a question about what is the threshold. Okay, the
same way there was one opinion, the foot and leg, there's another
opinion squirting blood, and here the rabbis' opinion is either foot or
leg. It's just more lenient.
So they don't, they're not disagreeing with the first part? Which part?
The part that says either the hand or the leg?
And they're saying no, you don't need both, you need either.
Right, so that would even on the first part.
Yes, yes, yes. Yeah, they're primarily responding to רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel.
It's a question how much they do or don't agree to the
squirting blood position. But they're primarily responding to רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel.
עד שתפרכס או ביד, ad shetiparkes o beyad, either foot, או ברגל,
o beragel, or a hind leg, או עד שתכשכש
בזנבה, o ad shetichashkesh biznavah, or like if it's, you know, waves
its tail. אחד בהמה דקה ואחד בהמה גסה, echad behemah dakah v'echad
behemah gasah, whether it is a small animal, meaning a sheep or
a goat, or a large animal like a cow. Now, not only
that, here's, here's a, here's another criterion, here's another way to determine
if it has enough life in it. בהמה דקה שפשטה ידה ולא
החזירה, behemah dakah shepashtah yadah v'lo hechzirah,
after you שחט shechted it, if it was a small animal like
a sheep or cow,
actually sheep or goat, and it's stuck out its leg, or its
arm, forearm, but did not pull it back in, פסולה, pesulah, that
is not enough movement. Even for the rabbis that have a lower
threshold. Why? שאינה אלא הוצאת נפש בלבד, she'einah ela hotzat nefesh bilvad,
because that is a natural way the body sort of reacts, you
know, spontaneous movement as the body is dying. And again, the point
here showing movement is since this animal was about to die, we
have to know that it was alive at the moment of שחיטה,
shechitah, that the act of שחיטה shechitah did it like, even when
you were half through it didn't already drop dead on us. So
it has to be something that shows some life force, not just
some natural sort of, you know, reaction of the body at the
moment of death. So the leg sticking out is a natural thing
the body will do and does not suffice. במה דברים אמורים שהייתה
בחזקת מסוכנת, bameh devarim amurim shehayitah bechezkat mesukenet, now all of this,
when is this true? במה דברים אמורים, bameh devarim amurim, when do
you need it to show these types of movements? שהייתה בחזקת מסוכנת,
shehayitah bechezkat mesukenet, if
there was an assumption that it was in, it was about, it
was like about to die. It doesn't exactly tell you how you
assess that, but, but anyway. אבל אם הייתה בחזקת בריאה, aval im
hayitah bechezkat beriah, if you assumed it was healthy, אפילו אין בה
אחד מכל הסימנים הללו כשירה, afilu ein bah echad mikol hasimanim halalu
kesherah, even without any of these signs it's valid. Because then who
needs an animal to thrash around? We're only doing this because we
are concerned it might have died before you finished שחט shechting it.
Okay, so that's all very nice, but the גמרא, Gemara, you know,
in a very nice shift here, rather than immediately jumping into discuss
which of these, you know, criteria, which of these signs is a
sufficient sign, front leg, back leg,
etc., takes, is now going to focus on the larger question here,
which is distinguishing between three categories: נבלה, nevelah, which as we've said
until now is an animal that dies without the benefit of שחיטה,
shechitah, טרפה, treifah, which is an animal that had שחיטה shechitah but
had an internal injury that meant it was going to die, and
now we have מסוכנת, mesukenet, which the משנה Mishnah assumes is כשר
kosher as long as it survives through the act of שחיטה, shechitah,
which is an animal that's about to die. The only real difference
between a מסוכנת mesukenet and a טרפה treifah is that a טרפה
treifah it's going to die soon because of an injury. מסוכנת mesukenet
it's going to die without the basis of an actual... טרף taraf
means to be torn, without some type of an injury. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara is going to first ask this question, you know,
since מסוכנת mesukenet is so close to either טרפה treifah or נבלה,
nevelah, right, it's close to נבלה nevelah because נבלה nevelah is actually
what happens when it actually does drop dead. מסוכנת mesukenet is about
to drop dead, so it's pretty close to נבלה. nevelah. It's also
pretty close to טרפה treifah in that it, you know, it will,
it has some condition that will cause it to die soon, which
is also pretty similar to טרפה. treifah. So how do you know
מסוכנת mesukenet is not a type of a נבלה nevelah or a
type of a טרפה? treifah? That is going to be the question
of the גמרא. Gemara. So let's take a look. מסוכנת ממאן דשריא,
mesukenet m'man de'sharya, okay,
who ever told you that a מסוכנת mesukenet was permissible? So the
גמרא Gemara says, ממאן תסק אדעתך דאסירה, m'man taseik ada'ateich de'asira, what
would make you think that it's prohibited? דכתיב, de'chtiv, as it says,
זאת החיה אשר תאכלו, zot hachayah asher tochlu,
this is the animal that you shall eat. חיה אכול, chayah echol,
an animal that can live you can eat. שאינה חיה לא תאכל,
she'einah chayah lo tochal, an animal that does not have the ability
to live you shall not eat. והא מסוכנת אינה חיה, ve'ha mesukenet
eina chayah, and this animal that is endangered, again, there's got to
be a better word than
endangered, this animal that is about to die is not going to
live. So therefore maybe it is forbidden based on that verse of
זאת החיה אשר תאכלו. zot hachayah asher tochlu. I would also say
תאכלו, tochlu, I would also say that, you know, there is a
discussion by טרפה, treifah, we've always said a טרפה treifah is an
animal with an injury that it will die, actually that is one
of the first basic debates about טרפה. treifah. Is a טרפה treifah
just a formal list that we have, הלכה
למשה מסיני, Halachah l'Moshe m'Sinai, certain types of injuries not based on
any predictive power, or is it based on the fact that these
injuries by a טרפה treifah are things that are assumed that they
will cause it to die within the
year? Although it's a
little bit it's a little debated. It's going to be at the
very beginning of the third פרק perek of that discussion. Okay. But
the camp that sets that position טריפה אינה חיה treifa eina chaya
that the problem of a טריפה treifa is that we assume the
animal won't survive with that injury, actually bases itself on this verse
זאת החיה אשר תאכלו. Zot hachaya asher tochlu. You can only eat
an animal that will live, not an animal that won't
live. So obviously it's a play on the word חיה. chaya. So
now what the גמרא Gemara is really saying is great, let's take
that concept that's at the heart of טריפה treifa that it won't
live with you know, you know for a year, won't live whatever,
and say that that itself should make the animal forbidden, that that
should make a מסוכנת mesukenes forbidden. Okay, so how do we so
how what makes us say not? So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: נבלה לא תאכל, Neveila lo tochal,
you cannot eat a נבלה, neveila, an actual carcass of an animal
that died without שחיטה. shechita. מכלל דמסוכנת שריה, Miklal demesukenes sharya,
so you see anything short of it actually having died as a
result of its illness or old age would be permissible. So if
it was just going to die and you shechted it you'd be
okay. It's only when it actually dies that it's a problem. דאי
סלקא דעתך מסוכנת אסירה, De'i salka da'atach mesukenes asira, because if it
was forbidden even when it as soon as it became infirm and
sick, השתא מחיים אסירה, hashtu mechayim asira, if it was already forbidden
when it was alive, לאחר מיתה מיבעיא? le'achar mita mibaya? How much
more why would you have to tell me that it's forbidden even
after it dies? Now we are assuming that this is the actual
trajectory here of the animal's life and death, meaning that first it
gets ill or first it gets old and then it drops dead.
The גמרא Gemara is going to say later that there's another possibility.
You have a totally healthy animal that all of a sudden somebody
cleaved it in half with a sword or all of a sudden
a lion attacked it. So it didn't die, it died through some
type of traumatic event, not through some natural slow death. But the
גמרא Gemara is now not considering that case, considering how do things
die? They die from sickness and old age. So if it was
already forbidden as a מסוכנת mesukenes before it died, of course it
would be forbidden once it already died. And since the תורה Torah
has to say it's only forbidden as a corpse, as a carcass,
as a נבלה, neveila, presumably until it died it was actually permitted.
Question?
Yes. How or does רוב rov come in? You know, you look
at it what do you mean?
Like by טריפה, treifa, can we wait till we get to טריפה
treifa by that?
Or even מסוכנת, mesukenes, like you know, do you say that most
animals this might look a little better than your standard מסוכנת, mesukenes,
you know this one's been torn by a lion? Or do you
say no, you know, most animals are torn by lions or whatever.
So by טריפה treifa we'll discuss. The general assumption is that it's
not just a statement of רוב rov by טריפה, treifa, it's actually
a statement that all animals that are טריפה treifas actually do die
within a year. But we'll discuss that. By מסוכנת, mesukenes, there's no
need to actually precisely define it because what we're actually saying is
I mean I guess to define it to require within the משנה
Mishna these סימנים, simanim, but it per se is not forbidden. So
exactly what is what are the conditions in which you call it
מסוכנת mesukenes to require the סימנים simanim in the משנה, Mishna, that
is not precisely defined. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara now says like
this:
Practically, do people even do this?
For Joe's reason I assume largely not. But old animals, I don't
know, quite possibly yes. Although the real contemporary meat industry is such
that you do not want to be putting out that quality of
meat and that really will probably hurt your business. So did they
do it on the farm? Probably yes. Right, you're a poor family
that only has whatever a few goats, a few sheep, and one
is about to die, so I assume the answer is yes. All
right, so now the גמרא Gemara so okay, so that's how we
know. We know because otherwise you would not have to forbid a
נבלה. neveila. So the גמרא Gemara says ודילמא היינו נבלה היינו מסוכנת.
vedilma hainu neveila hainu mesukenes. The גמרא Gemara says one minute, maybe
it's not true. Maybe a נבלה neveila is what the תורה Torah
calls the animal from the moment it's about to die. So it's
actually interesting, right? The גמרא Gemara does not immediately associate this with
טריפה, treifa, we might have. An animal that's alive that is going
to die soon. The גמרא, Gemara, because טריפה treifa at this stage
is thinking, no, that's an injury. It's immediately associating with that as
an earlier stage in the נבלה neveila continuum. It gets sick, it
gets old, it dies. So it's a נבלה neveila like a few,
a little bit earlier in the process. So the גמרא Gemara says
okay, your question is, but why would we need to forbid a
נבלה? neveila? So the answer is, well, maybe this is what a
נבלה neveila is. Maybe a נבלה neveila is the animal from the
moment it's about to die, not actually once it's already dead.
It's like dead man walking, right?
Exactly. So the גמרא Gemara says לא סלקא דעתך. lo salka da'atach.
That doesn't make sense. דכתיב dekasiv the verse says וכי ימות מן
הבהמה אשר היא לכם לאכלה, vechi yamut min habehema asher hi lachem
le'ochla, when an animal that you can eat dies הנוגע בנבלתה, hanogei'a
benivlatah, if you touch its נבלה neveila then you are טמא. tamei.
לאחר מיתה הוא דקרא רחמנא נבלה, le'achar mita hu dikra rachmana neveila,
only when it dies is it called a נבלה. neveila. מחיים לא
איקרי נבלה, mechayim lo ikri neveila,
when it's still alive it would not be called a נבלה. neveila.
A נבלה neveila is only after it dies. Of course remember the
גמרא Gemara before that led to all those interesting questions of like
an animal that's cut in half or cut from its back is
called a נבלה neveila and the גמרא Gemara sometimes said it's dead
and other times it said it's called a נבלה. neveila. although it's
still alive. So the גמרא, Gemara, you know exactly, which is again
all very interesting in this whole brain death question, you know exactly
what do we define as technical death, halachic death, is it a
נבילה neveila though we'll still say it's living because it's walking and
breathing? But anyway here the גמרא Gemara is saying that נבילה neveila
means that it is actually dead or whatever or maybe how technically
dead, however you might say it, but it's dead. So you can't
say that נבילה neveila starts just when it becomes מסוכנת. mesukenes. So
that's our proof that מסוכנת mesukenes is permissible. Only a נבילה neveila
is אסור. assur. Presumably when it's still alive even though it's about
to die it's still permissible. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says ודילמא
לעולם אימא לך היינו נבילה היינו מסוכנת. V'dilma l'olam eima lach hainu
neveila hainu mesukenes.
Maybe they'll say no, they're all fundamentally the same category. But your
question of why does it have to call it a נבילה neveila
only after it dies and forbid it only after it dies, maybe
the following: מחיים בעשה. Michayim b'aseh. When it's alive and about to
die, then it's forbidden by a positive command. What's the positive command?
זאת החיה אשר תאכלו. Zos hachaya asher tochalu.
Only eat something when it can live. But that's framed as a
positive מצוה. mitzvah. Eat something that can live. So when it's alive
and it's מסוכנת mesukenes it's forbidden by an עשה. aseh. לאחר מיתה,
L'achar misa, after it actually finally does die, בלאו, b'lav, then it's
forbidden by the negative prohibition of a נבילה neveila and then it
causes טומאה. tumah. So again maybe this is forbidden, it's the continuum
of נבילה, neveila, but because it hasn't died yet, it's not, it's
only forbidden by a positive command not by a negative command. So
how do we know it's not forbidden just a little bit less
than a נבילה neveila but still as part of that continuum? אלא,
Ella,
so here's how we know it's not forbidden. מדאמר רחמנא טריפה לא
תאכל, Mide'amar rachmana treifa lo sochal, do not eat a טריפה. treifa.
So again this as I said this has elements of a טריפה,
treifa, elements of a נבילה. neveila. מכלל דמסוכנת שרי. Miklal d'mesukenes shari.
So from here we can infer that a מסוכנת mesukenes is permissible.
How? So now it's not based on the idea that this is
a type of נבילה, neveila, it was part of the idea that
this was the normal lifespan of an animal. It becomes a מסוכנת,
mesukenes, then it dies. So if it's אסור assur when it's a
מסוכנת, mesukenes, why do you have to say it's אסור assur when
it dies? By a טריפה, treifa, obviously one animal could be a
טריפה treifa and another animal could be a מסוכנת mesukenes and they
never,
you know, their paths never cross. But nevertheless the גמרא Gemara is
saying why would you have to forbid a טריפה? treifa? A טריפה
treifa is a מסוכנת mesukenes plus. A טריפה treifa is a מסוכנת
mesukenes with an injury. So if something that's just a מסוכנת mesukenes
is forbidden, certainly a טריפה treifa that's a מסוכנת mesukenes by virtue
of an injury is certainly forbidden. So you would not need a
separate prohibition. So מדאמר רחמנא טריפה לא תאכל, Mide'amar rachmana treifa lo
sochal, don't eat a טריפה, treifa, מכלל דמסוכנת שרי, miklal d'mesukenes shari,
a normal מסוכנת mesukenes is permissible. ואי סלקא דעתך מסוכנת אסירה, V'i
salka dachach mesukenes assira, if a normal מסוכנת mesukenes is forbidden just
because it's about to die, השתא מסוכנת דלא מחסרא אסירה, hashta mesukenes
d'lo mechasra assira, an animal that's about to die even without an
injury that's not lacking anything, right, doesn't have a part of its
body torn away or lacking, even that is forbidden, טריפה מבעיא, treifa
mibeia, how much more so is an animal that's about to die
as a result of an injury? So why do you have to
forbid a טריפה treifa if the very fact that it's about to
die is enough to make it forbidden?
ודילמא היינו טריפה היינו מסוכנת. V'dilma hainu treifa hainu mesukenes. Maybe they
really are both equally forbidden, you know, here it doesn't mean the
same animal is both but yes, an animal is forbidden when it's
about to die and it's also forbidden as a טריפה. treifa. So
why do you need to forbid it twice? דלאו עליו בעשה ולא
תעשה. D'lav alav b'aseh v'lo sa'aseh. To get you twice. Because by
מסוכנת mesukenes when it's about to die, we said that's a positive
command. Only eat an animal that can live. That's our possibility, that
maybe an animal that's about to die is forbidden by the virtue
of the positive command of זאת החיה אשר תאכלו. Zos hachaya asher
tochalu. So it says okay, if it's מסוכנת mesukenes it's forbidden based
on a מצות עשה. mitzvas aseh. Once it also gets an internal
injury or once it also actually dies, then there's another negative prohibition.
So the reason the תורה Torah has to forbid a טריפה treifa
if it already forbade a מסוכנת mesukenes is that a normal מסוכנת
mesukenes is only a positive command, a טריפה, treifa, something that will
die as a result of an injury is forbidden on the basis
of a negative command. So basically the גמרא Gemara is saying there
is no basis to say that a מסוכנת mesukenes is not forbidden.
We have a פסוק pasuk that speaks of the importance of an
animal being able to live: זאת החיה אשר תאכלו. Zos hachaya asher
tochalu. The fact that it also forbids a נבילה neveila also forbids
a טריפה, treifa, those are to add additional prohibitions. But maybe from
the very moment that it is מסוכנת mesukenes it actually is forbidden.
Could you say that they're sort of both נבילה neveila and טריפה
treifa when you get them in both counts?
No, it's both מסוכנת mesukenes and a טריפה treifa and then when
it dies you mean, right, so that's an interesting question. When an
animal was a טריפה treifa that then died, is it a טריפה
treifa and a נבילה neveila or just a נבילה? neveila? Okay, we
normally assume just a נבילה. neveila. Okay, that a טריפה treifa is
defined as an animal that was שחט shechted with an injury, נבילה
neveila is an overriding definition. We'll see the next few lines in
the גמרא Gemara seem to sort of say not that way, but
let's take a look.
And then you know they meet מסוכנת mesukenes in there somehow.
Well we got the מסוכנת mesukenes in. מסוכנת mesukenes is forbidden without
it being a טריפה treifa once it's alive by a positive command.
All the other status just add additional prohibitions. But there's no logic
to exclude מסוכנת. mesukenes. Okay, that's what we're still saying.
Right.
No, no, no, understand but yeah you know well I may have
to articulate this a little
bit but... Thinking that you know
that it'd still be forbidden and our question was, you know, oh
no, but like, but then we see it's like a
טרפה, treifa, we see נבילה, neveila, and the answer is fine, so
they add other layers of prohibition, but מסוכנת mesukenes could still be
forbidden. The גמרא Gemara is still making that argument, okay, it hasn't
rejected it yet. Okay, so let's take a look. Okay, וליליף מלאו
דעשה ולא תעשה. v'leilyaf milav d'asei v'lo saasei. So the גמרא Gemara
says אם כן נבילה דכתב רחמנא למה לי? im kein neveila d'kasav
rachmana lama li? So why do you need to forbid a נבילה?
neveila? ומה מחיים קאי עליה בלאו ועשה, u'mah m'chayim kai aleiya b'lav
v'asei, if when it's alive it's forbidden by a negative prohibition and
a positive prohibition when it's a טרפה, treifa, right, the positive because
of מסוכנת, mesukenes, the negative because of טרפה, treifa, לאחר מיתה מבעיא?
l'achar misa mibaya? Why do you have to tell me that it's
forbidden after it drops dead? So obviously one answer could be it
dropped dead not as a result of being a טרפה. treifa. Okay,
so because otherwise this goes to the general question, why does an
animal that drops dead have to be forbidden? Wasn't it forbidden as
a טרפה? treifa? And the answer is it didn't have to be
a טרפה. treifa. And anyway, as I just said to Michael also,
נבילה neveila could be an overriding definition to that of טרפה. treifa.
But anyway, let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is. ודילמא היינו
נבילה היינו טרפה היינו מסוכנת. v'dilma hainu neveila hainu treifa hainu mesukenes.
The גמרא Gemara says no, maybe that could be one animal could
be all three, right, it's a טרפה treifa and it's also מסוכנת,
mesukenes, that's a positive and negative command, and then it drops dead
and it's also a נבילה. neveila. ולעבור עליו בשני לאוין ועשה. u'laavor
alav b'shnei lavin v'asei. Yeah, when it drops dead you get all
of the pro- all of the prohibitions because it dropped dead it's
a נבילה, neveila, because it had an injury it was a- it
was a טרפה, treifa, and because it was going to die with
or without the injury it's a מסוכנת. mesukenes. Now again, it's a
little funny what the question and the answer is because you could
have just said obviously that it dropped dead without having been a
טרפה treifa also. The assumption here that in a נבילה neveila you
also transgress for a טרפה treifa is something that we will have
to revisit, right, you would have said that once it's a נבילה
neveila and it actually dies without שחיטה shechita it's no longer defined
as a טרפה. treifa. But for now anyway the גמרא Gemara says
there's no reason to say there's not a prohibition of מסוכנת mesukenes
and it would add to all of these other prohibitions. So how
do we know that a מסוכנת mesukenes is permissible? אלא אמר גמרא
מהכא ela amar gemara meihacha from the following verse.
וחלב נבילה וחלב טרפה יעשה לכל מלאכה ואכול לא תאכלהו. v'cheilev neveila
v'cheilev treifa yeiaseh l'chol melacha v'achol lo socheiluhu. The fat of a
נבילה neveila and the fat of a טרפה treifa you can use
for any- for any work but you cannot eat it. Now what
is the purpose of that verse? So actually the simple sense probably
of that verse is to telling you that it's forbidden in eating
but you can derive benefit from it, like you know the classic
הלכה halachic point that it's אסור באכילה ומותר בהנאה. asur b'achila u'mudar
b'hana'ah. And that is what one גמרא Gemara says in פסחים Pesachim
that we learn from that verse, that that things that are just
because it says don't eat does not mean don't get benefit. Here
the תורה Torah explicitly telling you you can get benefit. The other
thing we actually also learn from it is that it says you
can be used for any work. Any work means even working to
let's say tan the leather of- hides of a קרבן korban or
something, after an animal is שחוט, shechut, which is to tell you
the idea that although a נבילה neveila causes טומאה, tumah, the חלב
cheilev of a נבילה, neveila, the חלב cheilev of the נבילה neveila
does not because you can use it for any labor even for
labor dealing with sanctified objects. Okay so we also learn from this
that the חלב cheilev of a נבילה neveila does not cause טומאה.
tumah. Now how is this relevant for us? So let's take a
look.
דאמר מר d'amar mar and we said למאי הלכתא אמרה תורה? l'mai
hilchasa amrah torah? Why did the תורה Torah have to say this-
this verse? Because I gave you two reasons but this teaching is
neither of those two. Either it's- either the reason of to- to
tell you you can get benefit or the reason to tell you
the חלב cheilev does not cause טומאה. tumah. But here we have
a different teaching what the purpose of this verse is. To tell
you the following: ואכול לא תאכלהו. v'achol lo socheiluhu.
To tell you that the prohibition of חלב cheilev applies although it's
already prohibited by the virtue of נבילה, neveila, right? The fat now
is prohibited from two directions: it is נבילה neveila and it's חלב,
cheilev, it's טרפה treifa and it's חלב. cheilev. So this is a-
normally something that we have questions about. Do you say איסור חל
על איסור? issur chal al issur? That when one thing is forbidden
it can become forbidden you know another level of prohibition can apply
to it. So that is what this is saying we are learning
from this verse. יבוא איסור נבילה ויחול על איסור חלב. yavo issur
neveila v'yachol al issur cheilev.
The prohibition of נבילה neveila can come and can take effect on
top the prohibition of חלב. cheilev. We mention חלב cheilev is the
first one because as soon as the animal is born it has
חלב cheilev in its body, the חלב cheilev is forbidden. The prohibition
of נבילה neveila or טרפה treifa comes later when it dies, when
it gets an injury. So this verse is telling you this is
the חלב cheilev of a נבילה, neveila, the חלב cheilev of a
טרפה. treifa. But it is actually- it is telling you although actually
it's not even clear in the verse, the verse maybe just אסר
asar as חלב, cheilev, but we're choosing to read this verse that
it's אסור asur from both categories. יבוא איסור טרפה ויחול על איסור
חלב. yavo issur treifa v'yachol al issur cheilev. The prohibition of טרפה
treifa can come and take effect on top of the איסור issur
of חלב. cheilev. Now what does this have to do with us
about מסוכנת? mesukenes? Let's take a look. Top of the עמוד ב.
amud beis.
Oh Jed is suggesting we should call מסוכנת mesukenes moribund. That's possible.
Thank you Jed. Okay so ואי סלקא דעתך טרפה היינו מסוכנת. v'ei
salka daitach treifa hainu mesukenes.
Now
if you say that a טרפה treifa is a מסוכנת, mesukenes, that
as soon as an animal with or without an injury is moribund
it is considered- it is forbidden as a מסוכנת. mesukenes. לכתוב רחמנא
חלב נבילה יעשה לכל מלאכה. lichtov rachmana cheilev neveila yeiaseh l'chol melacha.
You can use the חלב cheilev of a נבילה neveila for all
activity, right? Remember because that's
the- The חלב chelev of a נבילה. neveila. The חלב טרפה cheilev
treifah? לא תאכלו.
And just tell me not to eat the חלב chelev of a
טרפה. treifa. Why? Cause then I could have made a קל וחומר.
kal vachomer. Here would have been my קל וחומר. kal vachomer. ואנא
אמינא ומה מחיים אתי איסור טרפה וחייל על איסור חלב. va'ana amina
u'ma mechayim ati issur treifa vechayyal al issur chelev. If even the
חלב chelev of a טרפה treifa is forbidden, has two levels of
prohibition, חלב chelev and טרפה. treifa.
And I would say like this, that okay, now I'll make a
קל וחומר. kal vachomer. By a טרפה treifa even when that even
when it's alive the prohibition of טרפה treifa comes and takes effect
on top of the איסור חלב. issur chelev. לאחר מיתה מבעיא? le'achar
mita mibaya?
How much more so should that prohibition take effect even after the
animal dies. Now what does this mean? Right, so רש"י Rashi and
תוספות Tosafot are both asking
what does this mean? Why? Because it takes effect when it's alive,
should be a קל וחומר kal vachomer that it takes effect when
it's dead? So here's what רש"י Rashi says. רש"י Rashi is very
nice here and very conceptual. He says like this, he says, how
much, and notice remember the גמרא's Gemara's phrase before, this is why
this is such a great גמרא Gemara in terms of categories. The
גמרא's Gemara's phrase before, היינו טרפה היינו מסוכנת היינו נבילה. hainu treifa
hainu mesukenet hainu neveila. That's a pretty strange phrase, like it's all
three, they're all the same, well you know, they're not all the
same. So רש"י Rashi says no, because once you introduced מסוכנת mesukenet
into the mix, what you're saying is that the, and you're saying
מסוכנת mesukenet and טרפה treifa are variations of a theme. What you're
saying is is that the primary issue is that it's in the
process of dying. It's about to die, it's on that continuum. So
if you say that, טרפה treifa becomes a variation of מסוכנת. mesukenet.
It's really about that it's about to die. And נבילה neveila becomes
the next step in that continuum, it's about to die and it
dies. And they're all really part, you know, variations on a theme.
Once you say that, so if it's going to take effect at
an earlier stage in this process, you know, while the animal's still
alive, the prohibition will take effect. Certainly as that process gets sort
of more severe and actually does die, the prohibition of נבילה neveila
should certainly take effect because it's really just like טרפה treifa but
טרפה treifa made worse, or מסוכנת mesukenet made worse. So if it
takes place when the מסוכנת mesukenet טרפה treifa was earlier, certainly take
place, the נבילה neveila prohibition will take effect when it gets worse
when it actually dies. That's if you throw מסוכנת mesukenet into the
mix, then everything is just a continuum. But as soon as you
take מסוכנת mesukenet out of the mix, they're not really continuums. They're
totally different tracks. טרפה treifa is not because it's about to die,
you don't have to emphasize that, you could say טרפה treifa is
because it has an injury. And the injury is what identifies it.
נבילה neveila is because it died. So just because something is אסור
assur because of טרפה treifa doesn't mean it's going to be אסור
assur because of נבילה. neveila. So what רש"י Rashi said, I mean
this is really like, you know, brilliant is is that it's not
your classic קל וחומר. kal vachomer. Your classic קל וחומר kal vachomer
is apples and oranges, but if it's true for apples, קל וחומר
kal vachomer it's true for oranges. So what type of קל וחומר
kal vachomer is that? Just because the טרפה treifa prohibition applied when
it was alive, why should the נבילה neveila prohibition apply when it's
dead? But רש"י Rashi says that's exactly how things change when you
throw מסוכנת mesukenet into the mix. When you throw מסוכנת mesukenet into
the mix, it frames everything as being about to die and having
died, and everything is a continuum, היינו טרפה היינו מסוכנת היינו נבילה.
hainu treifa hainu mesukenet hainu neveila. So if it applies at an
earlier stage, it should certainly apply at a later stage and that's
the גמרא's Gemara's question. Since we don't say that, since we have
to say it's both prohibited as טרפה treifa and as נבילה, neveila,
means that those are two very conceptually distinct categories. And the only
way they become conceptually distinct categories is if you remove this broader
abstract concern of מסוכנת. mesukenet. Okay, so it says like this.
So תוספות Tosafot also has a different explanation?
It's a variation of רש"י. Rashi. רש"י Rashi is anyway much more,
I think, you know, powerful because of the reason I just said.
Okay, so אלא מדכתב רחמנא נבילה, ela midekhtav Rachmana neveila, since it
had to prohibit the fat of a נבילה, neveila, מכלל דטרפה לאו
היינו מסוכנת. miklal detreifa lav hainu mesukenet. The issue of טרפה, treifa,
I'm going to read just like רש"י, Rashi, is not fundamentally about
it being moribund. Because if it were, then
נבילה neveila טרפה treifa מסוכנת mesukenet would all be variations of the
same, and whenever it applies to one it would apply to the
other. And since they're not, you have to say separately the חלב
chelev of a טרפה treifa is forbidden, the חלב chelev of a
נבילה neveila is forbidden, obviously those are very distinct categories and that
becomes once you say מסוכנת mesukenet per se is not an issue.
Okay, so that's the גמרא's Gemara's conclusion. טרפה treifa is אסור, assur,
נבילה neveila is אסור, assur, just being about to die is not
the per se issue and therefore it doesn't put everything on the
same continuum. So מתקיף לה מר בר רב אשי, matkif lah Mar
bar Rav Ashi, so מר בר רב אשי Mar bar Rav Ashi
asks, ודילמא לעולם אימא לך היינו טרפה היינו מסוכנת. v'dilma le'olam eima
lach hainu treifa hainu mesukenet. Maybe I would tell you no, let's
go back, טרפה treifa and מסוכנת mesukenet are more or less the
same, one with an injury, one without. ודקאמרת נבילה דכתב רחמנא למה
לי? vedeka'amarat neveila dekhtav Rachmana lama li? So then why did the
תורה Torah also speak about the חלב chelev of a נבילה neveila
since everything is part of the same continuum, about to die and
having died and so on? So the גמרא Gemara says, לחלב נבילה
דלא אתי מכח מסוכנת, lechelev neveila d'lo ati mikoch mesukenet, when something
becomes a נבילה neveila not as part of that normal trajectory, not
as having become ill and sickly and then and dying. והיכי דמי,
ve'heichi dami, how could something become a נבלה nevelah not part of
that trajectory?
שעשאה גיסטרא, she'asa gistera, you cleaved it in half. So therefore maybe
that is a conceptually different נבלה. nevelah. You said once you introduced
מסוכנת, mesukenes, everything is a variation, about to die then actually dying,
and therefore you wouldn't need the תורה Torah to ever treat נבלה
nevelah separately. No, there is something that remains a conceptually distinct category
of נבלה, nevelah, died suddenly, was cleaved in half. And for that
reason, the תורה Torah had to treat נבלה nevelah separately.
That wouldn't be a טרפה?
treifah? So, well, not if you affected the נבלה nevelah status before
the טרפה treifah status, which there are ways of doing, okay, depending
on where you cut it and so on. So the גמרא Gemara
says, but the גמרא Gemara actually says what you're saying but from
the other angle. Let's take a look. גמרא Gemara says: התם נמי
אי אפשר דלא הויא מסוכנת פורתא מקמי דלפסוק לרובא. hasam nami ee
efshar delo harya mesukenes purta mikamei delifskay leruba. Okay, which is sort
of like what Michael said, you're going to make it a טרפה
treifah before you make it a נבלה. nevelah. The גמרא Gemara says,
well, even if that's not true, you'll certainly make it a מסוכנת
mesukenes before you make it a נבלה. nevelah. So you can't say
that it really completely escapes the trajectory of מסוכנת. mesukenes. So the
גמרא Gemara says: ואיבעית אימא, ve'iba'is eima, if you want I'll say,
and
here's a very technical point: לימא חלב נבלה וטרפה. leima cheilev nevelah
u'treifah.
Just say the fat of a נבלה nevelah and טרפה. treifah. חלב
חלב למה לי? cheilev cheilev lamei li? Why did it say חלב
נבלה cheilev nevelah and חלב chelev טרפה? treifah, Why does it have
that extra word of חלב? cheilev? To tell you the following: זו
היא שאין חלבה חלוק מבשרה. zu hi she'ein chelba chaluk mibesara.
This, a נבלה nevelah or טרפה, treifah, is something where there's no
different status between the fat and the meat. They're both אסור. assur.
The fat is אסור assur as fat and as טרפה, treifah. and
the meat is אסור assur because it's a טרפה. treifah ויש לך
אחרת, ve'yesh lecha acheres, you have something else that is similar to
a טרפה treifah and a נבלה, nevelah, שחלבה חלוק מבשרה, shechelba chaluk
mibesara,
that the fat is different than the meat. The fat is forbidden
and the meat is permissible. So meaning it's a very funny דרשה
drasha on a פסוק pasuk that's talking about fat, where we're saying:
but you have this extra word fat to tell you, only these
things are both the fat and the meat אסור. assur. There's something
else that the meat is just like this but the meat is
permissible. ואיזו, ve'eizo, what is this? זו מסוכנת, zu mesukenes, it's a
מסוכנת. mesukenes. So that's just a very technical point. There's an extra
word, it's not nearly as satisfying. But again, what is much more
satisfying is the fact that, you know, the גמרא Gemara says, and
you know, this is again a question of how do we conceptualize?
Do you see נבלה nevelah and טרפה treifah as on the same
continuum? Now if טרפה חיה, treifah chaya, the animal that has a
טרפה treifah can live, then you would never think to see them
on the same continuum. A טרפה treifah is an injury and a
נבלה nevelah is an animal that died without שחיטה. shechitah. If a
טרפה אינה חיה, treifah einah chaya, will not live, so then you
could sort of see that both of these are about, you know,
about sort of being on the process of dying, and so on.
Now even so though, טרפה treifah still does require that it have
an injury, so that at least does make them separate types of
concerns. Once you introduce
מסוכנת mesukenes into it, that it's all about will the animal survive
or not, that's where the גמרא Gemara says that puts everything on
the same continuum. So while we might have explanations, you get different
levels of prohibition, עשה, asei, לא תעשה, lo ta'asei, etc., we know
based on other verses and based on other things that we don't
see all of these as being on one continuum. We see them
as distinct, and therefore we know that מסוכנת mesukenes cannot be introduced
as a problem in itself. טרפה treifah. is a problem, נבלה nevelah
is a problem, but just being an animal that's about to die,
that's moribund, is not a problem. Okay, ואיבעית אימא מהכא, ve'iba'is eima
mehacha, and if you want, here's another verse we can learn it
from, and this is a fun verse because it gets us into
other areas by יחזקאל. Yechezkel. Okay, ואומר, va'omar, so יחזקאל Yechezkel says
to God: אהה ה׳ אלקים, ah'ha Hashem Elokim, behold, הנה נפשי לא
מטומאה, hinei nafshi lo metuma'ah, behold, my soul has not become טמאה,
teme'ah, ונבלה וטרפה לא אכלתי, u'nevelah u'treifah lo achalti, I did not
eat any נבלה nevelah or טרפה. treifah Interesting because it suggests the
idea that a טרפה treifah? causes טומאה, tumah, or it is referring
to טומאה tumah here as the more metaphorical טומאה tumah of prohibition.
But okay, מנעורי ועד עתה, mine'urai ve'ad ata, from my youth until
now, ולא בא בפי בשר פגול, ve'lo va befi basar pigul, and
no meat of פגול, pigul, right, when a כהן, kohen, יחזקאל Yechezkel
was a כהן, kohen, right, so if you think to do the
קרבן korban at the wrong time, that is meat of פגול, pigul,
and I didn't do any of these things wrong, okay. Even מסוכנת.
mesukenes. Well right, well that's basically going to be the response. But
before we get to that, the question is like, okay, what you,
this is your greatness, יחזקאל, Yechezkel, that you didn't eat נבלה nevelah
and טרפה? treifah. Nobody's supposed to eat נבלה nevelah and טרפה. treifah.
So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara is going to
analyze it: הנה נפשי לא מטומאה, hinei nafshi lo metuma'ah, my soul
has not become
טמאה, teme'ah, שלא הרהרתי ביום לבוא לידי טומאה בלילה. she'lo hirharti bayom
lavo lidei tumah balaylah. So the emphasis here seems to be נפשי,
nafshi, my soul, as opposed to let's say my body or something,
you know, having to do more with thoughts. So, you know, inner
soul, so thoughts. So it says, I did not have sexual thoughts
in the day that led to me having, you know, having seminal
emission at night, which causes טומאה, tumah, but again here's a concern
of טומאה tumah not just in the technical טומאה tumah that you
have to go to the מקוה, mikvah, but in the sense of
somehow like, you know,
defiling the soul, defiling the person because of filling the person with
these types of, you know, illicit sexual thoughts. So that's the first
way the גמרא Gemara reads that. Then it continues: ונבלה וטרפה לא
אכלתי מנעורי, u'nevelah u'treifah lo achalti mine'urai, I did not... I did
not eat even from the time I was young a נבלה neveilah
or טרפה. treifah So it says, so what does this mean? It
can't literally mean נבלה neveilah or טרפה treifah because then it's no
big deal, nobody's supposed to eat it. So we're going to explain
it the following
way: שלא אכלתי בשר כוס כוס מעולם. shelo achalti basar kus kus
me'olam. I never eat meat that we were saying שחוט שחוט שחוט
shchut, shchut, shchut meaning שחוט shechted before it dies, it's about to
die, quickly שחוט shecht it. So that's what he's calling נבלה neveilah
or טרפה meaning something that was about to become a נבלה. neveilah.
I never ate that type of a meat. כוס kus means, yeah,
שחוט shchut that was a מסוכנת, misukanis, okay, that was about to
die. ולא בא בפי בשר פיגול v'lo ba b'fi basar piggul and
no meat of פיגול piggul came into my mouth. What does this
mean? Again it can't be, it's assumed not
נבלה. neveilah. שלא אכלתי מבהמה שהורה בה חכם, shelo achalti mibeheimah shehorei
bah chacham, that I never ate meat that you needed to ask
a rabbi to give a פסק psak on, meaning any meat that
was ever doubtful whether it was כשר kosher or not and you
only knew it was כשר kosher because you got the ruling of
a חכם. chacham. Now that's not פיגול, piggul, but it is somehow
somehow questionable in the sense that a question was raised over it.
Now part of the problem with these things is that by having
יחזקאל Yechezkel say this as ideals, what you're also suggesting is that
that's something to strive for. That if you have a שאלה shailah
and you get a פסק, psak, if you're really פרום frum you
won't eat from it. Or if you have a מסוכנת, misukanis, if
you're really פרום frum you won't eat even from a
מסוכנת. misukanis. And there was I think there are sometimes stories about
people that they would say I would never ask on it, I
would never eat any meat that I ever had to ask a
שאלה shailah on like the story by יחזקאל. Yechezkel. I want to
free myself from even the shadow of any doubt of any halachic
question and so on.
Isn't that מהדרין? mehadrin? That's מהדרין. mehadrin.
In general I mean what do you mean?
Like מהדרין mehadrin isn't, מהדרין mehadrin
means something different to anybody.
Had there were no questions?
You mean like מהדרין שחיטה, mehadrin shechita, like גלאט? glatt? גלאט, glatt,
גלאט glatt is a specific type, גלאט. glatt. גלאט glatt is a
specific type of a thing which, yes, which means that the lungs
were smooth, but it more specifically means that there were not specific
types of questions. If somebody let's say has a גלאט glatt and
wants to know is this type of a thing, is this still
גלאט glatt or not and asks a פסק psak and the rabbi
says, yeah it's still גלאט, glatt, they're going to call it גלאט.
glatt. They're not going to say it's not גלאט glatt because they
had to ask a rabbi. So this means anything you had to
ask a rabbi, even if the rabbi says, yeah it's fine, the
fact that you had to ask a rabbi meant that it's somehow
not ideal. Right. So the question also becomes do you read this
יחזקאל Yechezkel thing as holding up some type of a religious ideal
or was this just like this was more like יחזקאל'ס Yechezkel's personal
asceticism and חומרה chumra and whatever, but it's not to be held
up as an ideal. That's always that's funny because even with the
whole idea of מסוכנת, misukanis, the גמרא Gemara never says that there's
a problem with מסוכנת misukanis and as long as it follows these
things it seems like it's totally fine and then it whole creates
this with יחזקאל. Yechezkel. The other issue is that יחזקאל Yechezkel says
I didn't have these
illicit sexual thoughts during the day. So that suggests that again compared
to the other things that that's an ideal that's not the standard.
The standard actually does not demand that. So תוספות Tosafot says but
there's other גמרות Gemaras that sound like that it is demanded, that
that is the standard that's demanded of everybody. So תוספות'ס Tosafot's answer
is, תוספות'ס Tosafot's first answer is it might be the standard but
it's an unrealistic standard that normal people always fail in this regard
and יחזקאל Yechezkel was able to succeed. Other answers that some ראשונים
Rishonim give about the issue of the sexual thoughts is there's difference
between sort of passing sexual thought and and really sort of like
focused trying to have them and pursuing them. So יחזקאל'ס Yechezkel's what
he said that he exceeded the standard was he didn't even have
these passing thoughts. But anyway back to us what is held out
here is implicitly it's permissible but also secondarily though that it is
that at least for יחזקאל Yechezkel it was not ideal. Ideal. So
let's just finish this. משום רבי נתן אמרו, Mishum Rebbe Natan amru,
for רבי נתן Rebbe Natan they said what is this בשר פיגול?
basar piggul? שלא אכלתי מבהמה שלא הורמו מתנותיה. shelo achalti mibeheimah shelo
hurmu matnoteha. Although I'm a
כהן Kohen I never ate from an animal that they did not
separate out the gifts. You're supposed to give from an animal gifts
to a כהן: Kohen: זרוע לחיים וקיבה, zro'a lechayayim v'keivah, the forearm
and the maw and the whatever and the stomach. So it is
not like תרומה terumah actually there's a debate but we're assuming it's
not like תרומה. terumah. By תרומה terumah if you give a כהן
Kohen your grain without having taken תרומה, terumah, it's a prohibition of
טבל, tevel, it's a serious prohibition of eating it, the grain is
not כשר. kosher. By meat without separating out the gifts the meat
is still כשר. kosher. It's just the gifts haven't been separated out.
So יחזקאל Yechezkel says if somebody served me a steak from an
animal that didn't have the gifts separated out, although I'm a כהן,
Kohen, although the meat is permissible and although I could eat from
any part of it because even as a כהן Kohen I could
take the part that's supposed to go to a כהן, Kohen, since
this person did not do the right thing, did not first separate
out the gifts to the כהן, Kohen, I refused to eat from
it. Now I do think by the way it's interesting here the
variations on פיגול piggul that I don't know how either of these
are פיגול, piggul, they don't relate to the improper thought, but what
I do know is that פיגול piggul is from the world of
קרבנות, korbanot, of קדשים, kodshim, יחזקאל Yechezkel was post חורבן churban and
the question is who is presented here as... standing in stead of
this idea of wrong thoughts of a כהן. Kohen. You know, so
in one case it is the second one emphasizes the כהן Kohen
aspect, right? There's something the matter with this as a type of
קדשים Kodshim going to the כהן Kohen the same way פיגול Pigul
you have a wrong thought, so here you did something wrong with
it. But it's very much within the world of כהנים. Kohanim. Okay,
retains that aspect of it. The other idea that a Rabbi did
not rule about it, הורה בו חכם, Hor'eh Bo Chacham, is very
much sort of the shift, right? that happens after the חורבן Churban
from a temple-based Judaism to a rabbinic-based Judaism and a תורה-based Torah
Judaism. So he is sort of saying anything that there was פיגול
Pigul is sort of something that, you know, because of the role
of the כהן, Kohen, you know, the כהן's Kohen relationship to the
meat and the thought and whatever, the role of the כהן Kohen
was
done correctly. So here too when there's some type of a role
that the Rabbi is doing, you know, and there's some question that's
arisen, I want to keep away from it. So what's interesting to
me is less the exact comparison to פיגול Pigul because it's a
stretch, but the fact that it replaces כהן Kohen with Rabbi, with
חכם, Chacham, you know, that's sort of what I see as going
on. Anyway, so continuing on in the גמרא. Gemara. So,
אי
אמרת בשלמא שריא, ee amarta bishlama sharaya, if מסוכנת mesukenes is permissible,
היינו רבותיה דיחזקאל, hynu revusei de'Yehezkel, that is the חידוש chiddush of
יחזקאל Yehezkel what he's doing greater, he's not eating a מסוכנת. mesukenes.
אלא אי אמרת אסירא, Ela ee amarta asira, if מסוכנת mesukenes is
forbidden, מאי רבותיה דיחזקאל, mai revusei de'Yehezkel, what is the big deal
about יחזקאל? Yehezkel? He didn't do anything better than anyone else. So
as long as you want to don't want to interpret נבילה וטריפה
neveilah ve'treifah literally, why do you interpret it as מסוכנת mesukenes if
מסוכנת mesukenes is also forbidden? Okay, so again it's pretty funny because
it's obviously not in the פסוק, pasuk, it's about how the Rabbis
reinterpret the פסוק, pasuk, so it's a little circular based on the
way the Rabbis reinterpret the פסוק, pasuk, we see that מסוכנת mesukenes
is permissible. Okay, but who told the Rabbis that? So anyway, but
that's the other פסוק pasuk that we learn it from. Now the
גמרא Gemara finally turns to some of the now that we decided
that מסוכנת mesukenes is permissible, that it's taken out of this continuum
of טריפה treifah נבילה neveilah and so on, which allows טריפה treifah
נבילה neveilah to each take different paths, we now are able to
take a step back and to actually analyze, not take a step
back, if you would, get more into the specific and analyze what
exactly are the definitions of מסוכנת mesukenes and so on. By the
way, I should also say the תוספות Tosfos about this issue about
מסוכנת, mesukenes, there's one phrase in תוספות Tosfos here where I think
he says מאיסא. me'isa.
I'll try to find the phrase.
Maybe it was רש"י. Rashi. Hold on.
Yeah, look at the fourth line of the רש"י, Rashi, here the
wide line, it starts with the word רבותיה. revusei. דאף על גב
דשריא, Ve'af al gav desharaya, although מסוכנת mesukenes is permissible, כיון דמאיסא
לא אכלתי, kivan d'me'isa lo achaltay, because it is disgusting I didn't
eat it. So this makes it sound like יחזקאל's Yehezkel concern with
מסוכנת mesukenes had nothing to do with halachically it's not an ideal,
had to do with just a type of a, you know, aesthetic,
so like ick, like gross, you want to eat an animal that
was about to die, lech. Now if that's true it's a little
funny that he's praising himself to God because of that and it
doesn't exactly fit with the other things like הורה בו חכם, hor'eh
bo chacham, but what it does speak about is is that it's
not necessarily an ideal that everybody should strive to. You know, there's
if you want to be so פרום frum that you're not going
to eat on something that required a פסק, psak, that's your issue,
that's not necessarily a חומרא chumrah that people should strive to. You've
got your hang ups about those things, for you that's inappropriate. So
there's something I think nice about this רש"י Rashi that it makes
those state this גמרא Gemara about יחזקאל Yehezkel as his sort of
subjective sort of חומרות, chumrot, and not something that necessarily is held
out as an objective ideal. It would certainly make life very hard
for most people if you could never do so, you know, if
you had this חומרא chumrah out there to never never do anything
that required a פסק, psak, that required a שאלה, sheilah, you know,
to a Rabbi. Okay, maybe it's specifically around food. What?
Wouldn't need Rabbis.
Wouldn't need Rabbis, right? Maybe it's specifically around food, there tends to
be a lot more concerns of things that are going in your
body, you know, as having that, you know, and as opposed to
just other areas. Okay. So now we get to the גמרא Gemara
to the more halachic discussion. Let's take a look. היכי דמי מסוכנת?
Heichidami mesukenes? What are what exactly is a מסוכנת? mesukenes? So because
the משנה Mishnah and the גמרא Gemara never said what the parameters
were. So אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav,
כל שמעמידין אותה ואינה עומדת. kol she'ma'amidin otah ve'einah omedet. You try
to stand it up and it collapses. It can't stand on its
own. It can't even stay standing on its own.
Yeah but then you say that can also even be if an
injury.
All right, presumably barring localized problems. רב חנינא בר שמיה משמיה דרבא
אמר, Rav Chanina bar Shmaya mishmei de'Rava amar, and now we have
another statement in the name of רבא Rava to even to add
to this, אפילו אוכלת בקיוות, afilu ochelet bikyot, even if it can
sort of chew on wood, meaning even if let's say, you know,
its mouth and whatever, it's still strong in its mouth and it
can chew on wood chips, but if it doesn't have the strength
to remain standing, it's considered מסוכנת. mesukenes. That is not contrary evidence.
רמי בר יחזקאל אמר, Rami bar יחזקאל amar, אפילו אוכל קורות, afilu
ochel korot, same idea except making it a more extreme statement, even
if it eats beams. Beams, beams of wood. Okay, so
it could have great teeth and great ability to chew, but if
it can't stand up, it's a problem. בסורא מתני הכי. be Sura
matni hachi. That's how they taught it in Sura. בפומבדיתא מתני הכי.
be Pumbedita matni hachi. Here's how they taught in Pumbedita, more or
less the same. היכי דמי מסוכנת? heichi dami mesukenes? What's a מסוכנת?
mesukenes? אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, כל
שמעמידין אותה ואינה עומדת. kol shema'amidin osah ve'eina omedes. So רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda says in the name of רב, Rav, if you stand
it up and it doesn't remain standing, ואפילו אוכלת פקעות. ve'afilu ocheles
peka'os. And here the original statement of רב יהודה Rav Yehuda in
the name of רב Rav incorporated this line, even if it eats
wood, wood chips, and then רמי בר יחזקאל Rami bar Yechezkel came
and added אמר אפילו אוכלת קורות, amar afilu ocheles koros, even if
it eats beams, beams of wood, it doesn't matter if it can't
stand up, remain standing, it is a מסוכנת. mesukenes. Okay, let's just
start the next topic, or whatever the obviously related topic. אשכחינהו שמואל
לתלמידי דרב. ashkechinhu Shmuel letalmidei deRav. So שמואל Shmuel found the students
of רב. Rav. אמר להו, amar lehu, he bumped into them somewhere
in the market, he said to them, מאי אמר רב במסוכנת? mai
amar Rav bemesukenes? Did רב Rav say anything interesting today about a
מסוכנת, mesukenes, presumably that they knew they were learning that in the
הישיבות? ha'Yeshivos? Okay,
so he happens to say to them, does רב Rav have any
interesting חידושים chiddushim about the מסוכנת? mesukenes? אמרו ליה, amru lei, they
said to him, הכי אמר רב, hachi amar Rav, this is what
רב Rav says, top of ל"ח עמוד א': lamed ches amud aleph:
גועה והטילה רעי וכיסקסה באזנה, go'ah vehitilah re'i vekiskesah beoznah,
הרי זו פירכוס. harei zu pirchus. Add it to the list of
the משנה, Mishna, רש"י Rashi says this following list is 'ors', not
'ands', any of these three things which constitute movement that the animal
would be okay. Remember it needs to move if it's מסוכנת mesukenes
when you שחט shacht it. So what is גועה? go'ah? It's basically
lowing, okay, moaning or lowing actually, והטילה רעי vehitilah re'i or defecating,
or וכיסקסה באזנה vekiskesah beoznah moving its ear. Any of those things
during the act of שחיטה shechitah would be considered movement and be
okay for a מסוכנת. mesukenes. So let's just see his response. אמר
להו, amar lehu, he said back to them, איצטריכא ליה לאבא לאזועי
אוני? itztarichah lei le'Abba le'azu'ei unei?
אבא Abba requires,
which is a name for רב, Rav, I'll talk about that in
a minute, requires the movement of an ear? Apparently the movement of
an ear was very difficult for an animal that's in the process
of being שחט. shachted. Okay, so other types of larger body parts
are actually easier than moving your ear. I don't know, I can't
wiggle my ears, I can move my other body parts. So apparently
that was considered to be a very high standard to have to
move an ear. Right, he's adding, but I guess he felt it
funny, good point, it's just okay, that's one possibility of many, but
he still feels that that is like a bizarre thing to mention
because that requires a lot of life force. It's maybe distracting to
mention something like that. Why, and why is that strange? שאני אומר,
she'ani omer, because I say, says שמואל, Shmuel, כל שאינו דברים שהמיתה
עושה, kol she'eino devarim shehamisah osah, anything that's not a movement based
on a natural result of מיתה, misah, death, any additional movement that's
just does not a natural sort of body response to death would
constitute, and you don't even need to get to the point of
the moving of the ear. Now Michael is right, he didn't demand
the move, at least according to רש"י, Rashi, this list is 'ors',
not 'ands', so he didn't demand the moving of an ear, but
again, you don't want to list things that suggest higher standards, okay?
And he says really anything that's a movement that's not based on
death is fine. One last comment about אבא, Abba, why does he
call him אבא? Abba? So רש"י Rashi says that that was an
honorific, like you know, father is like a father figure, it's an
honorific. תוספות Tosafos says אבא Abba actually was רב's Rav original name,
and the phrase רב Rav was actually the honorific, and he says
you know, great rabbis like רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi was
רבי. Rebbi. So רב Rav was רב. Rav. Think about nowadays, right?
People call הרב HaRav Soloveitchik the רב. Rav. In Israel, you know
who the רב Rav is? הרב HaRav Kook. So the רב Rav
is the רבי Rebbi that you feel is the big authority and
so on. So actually תוספות Tosafos says that אבא Abba was his
name and רב Rav was just his honorific. Okay, so anyway we
will end here to continue tomorrow with definitions of פירכוס. pirchus.